I'd like to share with you a discovery that I made a few months ago
أريد أن أشارككم بشيء اكتشفته منذ بضعة أشهر
while writing an article for Italian Wired.
عندما كنت أكتب مقالًا لمجلة "وايرد" الايطالبة
I always keep my thesaurus handy whenever I'm writing anything,
يجب عليّ أن أبقي قاموسا للمفردات بقربي عند كتابتي لأي شيء
but I'd already finished editing the piece,
وعندما انتهيت من كتابة المقال
and I realized that I had never once in my life
أدركت أنني لم أبحث قط
looked up the word "disabled" to see what I'd find.
عن مرادف كلمة "معاق" لأرى ماذا سوف أجد
Let me read you the entry.
لأقرأ عليكم ماذا وجدت
"Disabled, adjective: crippled, helpless, useless, wrecked,
"معاق," صفة: مشلول, عاجز, غير مفيد, محطم
stalled, maimed, wounded, mangled, lame, mutilated,
مقعد, مشوه, مجروح, متلف, أعرج
run-down, worn-out, weakened, impotent, castrated, paralyzed, handicapped,
متهدم ، مهترئ ، مضغف , مخصي ، مشلول ، معاق
senile, decrepit, laid-up, done-up, done-for, done-in
مصاب بالخرف, بال
cracked-up, counted-out;
مكسور, لا يعد
see also hurt, useless and weak.
انظر الى: مصاب, عديم الفائدة و ضعيف
Antonyms, healthy, strong, capable."
المتضادات: صحي, قوي, قادر
I was reading this list out loud to a friend and at first was laughing,
كنت أقرأ هذه القائمة على صديقتي وكنت أضحك في البداية
it was so ludicrous,
لأنه شيئ مثير للسخرية
but I'd just gotten past "mangled," and my voice broke,
ولكن عندما وصلت لكلمة "متلف" تقطع صوتي
and I had to stop and collect myself
وتوقفت لأجمع نفسي
from the emotional shock and impact that the assault from these words unleashed.
من الصدمة العاطفية الناتجة عن هذه الكلمات
You know, of course, this is my raggedy old thesaurus
كان هذا داخل قاموسي القديم
so I'm thinking this must be an ancient print date, right?
فظننت أنها تاريخ الطباعة أثري
But, in fact, the print date was the early 1980s,
ولكن في الواقع كان تاريخ الطباعة في اوائل الثمانينيات
when I would have been starting primary school
وكان هذا عندما كنت قد بدأت للتو من المرحلة الابتدائية
and forming an understanding of myself outside the family unit
والنظر الى نفسي من خارج الدائرة العائلية
and as related to the other kids and the world around me.
وأقارن نفسي بالأطفال والعالم من حولي
And, needless to say, thank God I wasn't using a thesaurus back then.
ويجب أن أشكر الله لعدم استخدامي قاموسا للمفردات في ذلك الوقت
I mean, from this entry, it would seem that I was born into a world
لأنه كما يبدو من هذه المعاني أنني قد ولدت في عالم
that perceived someone like me
لا يرى للناس الذين مثلي
to have nothing positive whatsoever going for them,
أي شيء ايجابي يحدث لهم
when in fact, today I'm celebrated for the opportunities and adventures
وعندما في الواقع يحتفل العالم اليوم بفرصي ومغامراتي
my life has procured.
تغيرت حياتي
So, I immediately went to look up the 2009 online edition,
وذهبت على الفور لأبحث عن عن المفردات المحدثة لسنة ٢٠٠٩ على الانترنت
expecting to find a revision worth noting.
على أمل أن أجد تغييرا جدير بالملاحظة
Here's the updated version of this entry.
وهذا ما وجدت
Unfortunately, it's not much better.
وللأسف فانها ليست أحسن بكثير
I find the last two words under "Near Antonyms," particularly unsettling:
وأقلقتني كثيرا آخر كلمتين في المتضادات بالتحديد
"whole" and "wholesome."
"كامل" و "مفيد"
So, it's not just about the words.
فالمسألة ليست فقط عن الكلمات
It's what we believe about people when we name them with these words.
ولكن عن ما نراه عن الناس عندما نسميهم بهذه الكلمات
It's about the values behind the words, and how we construct those values.
وعن المباديء التي وراء هذه الكلمات وكيفية بنائهن
Our language affects our thinking and how we view the world
لغتنا تؤثر في طريقة تفكيرنا و كيفية النظر الى العالم
and how we view other people.
ورؤية الناس الآخرين
In fact, many ancient societies, including the Greeks and the Romans,
وفي الواقع كان العديد من المجتمعات القديمة, بما في ذلك اليونانيون والرومان
believed that to utter a curse verbally was so powerful,
يعتقدوا بأن نطق أية لعنة كان قويا جدا
because to say the thing out loud brought it into existence.
لأنهم بنطقها بصوت عال يأتون بها الى الوجود
So, what reality do we want to call into existence:
فما هي الحقيقية التي نريد أن نأتي بها الى الوجود
a person who is limited, or a person who's empowered?
شخص محدود أم شخص قوي؟
By casually doing something as simple as naming a person, a child,
وبفعل شيء بسيط مثل تسمية شخص أو طفل ما
we might be putting lids and casting shadows on their power.
قد نضع غطيّ وظلالا على قوتهم
Wouldn't we want to open doors for them instead?
ألا نريد أن نفتح لهم أبوابا بدلا من ذلك؟
One such person who opened doors for me was my childhood doctor
وكان احدى الأشخاص الذين فتحوا لي أبوابا طبيبي في طفولتي
at the A.I. duPont Institute in Wilmington, Delaware.
في معهد أ.ي.دو بونت في ويلمنجتون-ديلاوير
His name was Dr. Pizzutillo,
كان اسمه الدكتور بيتزولو
an Italian American, whose name, apparently,
وكان أمريكي من أصل ايطالي
was too difficult for most Americans to pronounce,
وصعب على معظم الأمريكيين لفظ اسمه
so he went by Dr. P.
فعرف باسم وهو الدكتور بي
And Dr. P always wore really colorful bow ties
كان يلبس الدكتور بي ربطات عنق ملونة
and had the very perfect disposition to work with children.
وكان يحسن التصرف مع الأطفال كثيرا
I loved almost everything about my time spent at this hospital,
أحببت كل شيء تقريبا في الوقت الذي أمضيته في المستشفى
with the exception of my physical therapy sessions.
باستثناء جلسات العلاج الطبيعي
I had to do what seemed like innumerable repetitions of exercises
فكان على أن أقوم تمارين مكثفة
with these thick, elastic bands -- different colors,
باستخدام مطاطات عريضة بألوان مختلفة
you know -- to help build up my leg muscles,
لتقوية عضلات رجلي
and I hated these bands more than anything --
وكنت أكره هذه المطاطات أكثر من كل شيء
I hated them, had names for them. I hated them.
كرهتهن, أطلقت عليهن أسامي. كرهتهن
And, you know, I was already bargaining, as a five year-old child,
وهل تعلمون أنني قد بدأت بالمساومة ، كطفلة تبلغ خمس سنوات من العمر
with Dr. P to try to get out of doing these exercises,
مع دكتور بي لأحاول التهرب من من القيام بهذه التمارين
unsuccessfully, of course.
ومن دون جدوى بالطبع
And, one day, he came in to my session --
وفي يوم من الأيام دخل الى الجلسات
exhaustive and unforgiving, these sessions --
التي تضني ولا ترحم
and he said to me, "Wow. Aimee, you are such a strong and powerful little girl,
وقال لي "آيمي, كم أنت فتاة قوية,
I think you're going to break one of those bands.
اعتقد بأنك سوف تقطعين احدى هذه المطاطات
When you do break it, I'm going to give you a hundred bucks."
وعندما تقطعينها, سوف أعطيك مئة دولار"
Now, of course, this was a simple ploy on Dr. P's part
كانت هذه خطة بسيطة بالتأكيد من قبل دكتور بي
to get me to do the exercises I didn't want to do
لجعلي بالقيام بالتمارين التي لم أرد القيام بها
before the prospect of being the richest five-year-old in the second floor ward,
بغض النظر عن احتمال أن أكون أغنى طفلة تبلغ خمس سنوات من العمر في جناح الطابق الثاني
but what he effectively did for me was reshape an awful daily occurrence
وما فعل هذا بي هو أنه أعاد تشكيل حدثا يوميا فضيع بالنسبة لي
into a new and promising experience for me.
الى تجربة جديدة واعدة
And I have to wonder today to what extent his vision
ويجب أن أتساءل اليوم ، إلى أي مدى كانت رؤيته
and his declaration of me as a strong and powerful little girl
وتصريحه بأني فتاة قوية
shaped my own view of myself
قد شكل وجهة نظري عن نفسي
as an inherently strong, powerful and athletic person well into the future.
كانسانة قوية بالوراثة، ورياضية في المستقبل
This is an example of how adults in positions of power
هذا مثال لكيف يستطيع البالغين الذين في مراكز السلطة
can ignite the power of a child.
أن يشعلوا قوة الطفل
But, in the previous instances of those thesaurus entries,
ولكن ، كما في الحالات السابقة للمعاني التي كانت في القاموس
our language isn't allowing us to evolve into the reality that we would all want,
فان لغتنا لا تسمح لنا بمواكبة الواقع الذي نريده جميعا
the possibility of an individual to see themselves as capable.
واحتمال أن يعتبر الفرد نفسه قادرا
Our language hasn't caught up with the changes in our society,
فلغتنا لم تواكب التغيرات التي حدثت في المجتمع
many of which have been brought about by technology.
واتي أتى كثير منها مع التكنولوجيا
Certainly, from a medical standpoint,
وبلا شك من وجهة نظر طبية
my legs, laser surgery for vision impairment,
فرجلي وعملية الليزر التي قمت بها لتصحيح نظري
titanium knees and hip replacements for aging bodies
واستبدال مفاصل الورك والركبة بالتيتانيوم لمحاربة الشيخوخة
that are allowing people to more fully engage with their abilities,
والتي تسمح للناس بالتفاعل الكامل مع قدراتهم
and move beyond the limits that nature has imposed on them --
والتحرك خارج حدود الطبيعة التي فرضت عليهم
not to mention social networking platforms
ناهيك عن منابر الشبكات الاجتماعية
allow people to self-identify, to claim their own descriptions of themselves,
والتي تسمح للناس بأن يبرزوا هويتهم والمطالبة بصفاتهم الشخصية
so they can go align with global groups of their own choosing.
حتى يتمكنوا من الانحياز مع مجموعات عالمية من اختيارهم
So, perhaps technology is revealing more clearly to us now
فربما استطاعت التكنولوجيا أن تكشف الغطاء
what has always been a truth:
عما كانت الحقيقة دائما
that everyone has something rare and powerful to offer our society,
و هي ان الجميع لديه شيء نادر وقوي لتقديمه لمجتمعنا
and that the human ability to adapt is our greatest asset.
وقدرة الإنسان على التكيف هي ثروتنا الحقيقية
The human ability to adapt, it's an interesting thing,
فقدرة الإنسان على التكيف شيء مثير للاهتمام
because people have continually wanted to talk to me about overcoming adversity,
لأن الناس يريدوا أن يتحدثوا معي باستمرار عن التغلب على المحن
and I'm going to make an admission:
وسوف أعترف الآن
This phrase never sat right with me,
بأن هذه العبارة لم تحلو لي
and I always felt uneasy trying to answer people's questions about it,
وكنت أشعر دائما بعدم الارتياح للإجابة عن أسئلة الناس عن ذلك
and I think I'm starting to figure out why.
وأعتقد أنني بدأت أعرف سبب ذلك
Implicit in this phrase of "overcoming adversity"
فهمنا من هذه العبارة عن التغلب على المحن
is the idea that success, or happiness,
أن فكرة النجاح، أو السعادة
is about emerging on the other side of a challenging experience
ينشأن على الجانب الآخر من أي تجربة صعبة
unscathed or unmarked by the experience,
سالمين وغير متأثرين من هذه التجربة
as if my successes in life have come about from an ability
كما لو كانت نجاحاتي في الحياة صادرة من قدرتي
to sidestep or circumnavigate the presumed pitfalls of a life with prosthetics,
لتجنب اعاقات الحياة مع الأطراف الاصطناعية
or what other people perceive as my disability.
أو ما يراه الناس كاعاقتي
But, in fact, we are changed. We are marked, of course, by a challenge,
ولكن في الواقع ، نحن نتغير بطبيعة الحال من قبل أي تحدي
whether physically, emotionally or both.
سواء كان جسديا أو عاطفيا أو كليهما
And I'm going to suggest that this is a good thing.
وسوف أقترح أن هذا شيئا جيد
Adversity isn't an obstacle that we need to get around
المحنة لا تشكل لنا عائقا يجب التغلب عليه
in order to resume living our life.
لاستئناف العيش في حياتنا
It's part of our life.
ولكنها جزئا من حياتنا
And I tend to think of it like my shadow.
وأميل الى التفكير بأنها كظلي
Sometimes I see a lot of it, sometimes there's very little,
في بعض الأوقات أرى منها كثيرا و البعض الآخر قليلا
but it's always with me.
و لكنها دائما معي
And, certainly, I'm not trying to diminish the impact, the weight, of a person's struggle.
وانني لا أقلل من شأن نضال أي شخص بالتأكيد
There is adversity and challenge in life,
فهنالك محن وتحديات في الحياة
and it's all very real and relative to every single person,
وهي حقيقية ومتصلة بكل انسان
but the question isn't whether or not you're going to meet adversity,
ولكن السؤال هو ليس اذا ما سوف تواجه المحن أم لا
but how you're going to meet it.
ولكن كيف سوف تواجههن
So, our responsibility is not simply shielding those we care for from adversity,
فمسؤوليتنا ليست حماية من نهتم بهم من المحن
but preparing them to meet it well.
ولكن اعدادهم لمواجهتها بطريقة صحيحة
And we do a disservice to our kids
ونحن نسيء بأطفالنا
when we make them feel that they're not equipped to adapt.
عندما نشعرهم بأنهم غير مهيأين للتأقلم معها
There's an important difference and distinction
هناك فرق مهم
between the objective medical fact of my being an amputee
بين الواقع الطبي بكوني مبتورة الساقين
and the subjective societal opinion of whether or not I'm disabled.
ورأي المجتمع في كوني معاقة أم لا
And, truthfully, the only real and consistent disability I've had to confront
وفي الحقيقية, الاعاقة الوحيدة التي كان يجب أن أواجهها دائما
is the world ever thinking that I could be described by those definitions.
هي كيف باستطاعة الناس أن يصفونني بتلك التعاريف
In our desire to protect those we care about
في رغبتنا لحماية الذين نهتم بهم
by giving them the cold, hard truth about their medical prognosis,
وباعطائهم الحقيقة الباردة عن تشخيصهم الطبي
or, indeed, a prognosis on the expected quality of their life,
أو بالأحرى تشخيصا عن جودة حياتهم المتوقعة
we have to make sure that we don't put the first brick in a wall
يجب علينا التأكد بعدم وضع الطوبة الأولى في الجدار
that will actually disable someone.
الذي سوف يتسبب في النهاية في اعاقة أحد
Perhaps the existing model of only looking at what is broken in you
وربما تكون فكرة البحث عما كسر بداخلك
and how do we fix it, serves to be more disabling to the individual
وكيفية اصلاحه, أكثر اعاقة
than the pathology itself.
من المرض بحد ذاته
By not treating the wholeness of a person,
بعدم التعامل مع كمالية الانسان
by not acknowledging their potency,
وعدم الاقرار بقوتهم
we are creating another ill on top of whatever natural struggle they might have.
فنحن نخلق مرضا آخر فوق ما يصارعونه
We are effectively grading someone's worth to our community.
نحن نصنف الناس بما قد تكون قيمتهم لمجتمعنا
So we need to see through the pathology
فيجب علينا النظر لما بعد المرض
and into the range of human capability.
وداخل نطاق القدرة البشرية
And, most importantly, there's a partnership
والأهم من ذلك, أن هنالك شراكة
between those perceived deficiencies
بين فهم هذه النواقص
and our greatest creative ability.
وأعظم ما نملك من قدراتنا الابداعية
So it's not about devaluing, or negating, these more trying times
والفكرة ليست حول التقليل من قيمة ، أو نفي هذه الأوقات العصيبة
as something we want to avoid or sweep under the rug,
أو كشيء نريد أن نتفاداه أو نكنسه تحت السجادة
but instead to find those opportunities wrapped in the adversity.
ولكن لايجاد الفرص المتواجدة في هذه المحن
So maybe the idea I want to put out there is
وربما الفكرة التي أحاول أن أطرحها
not so much overcoming adversity
هي ليس التغلب على المحن
as it is opening ourselves up to it,
ولكن تقبل أنفسنا لها
embracing it,
واحتضانها
grappling with it,
والصراع معها
to use a wrestling term,
عند استخدام مصطلح المصارعة
maybe even dancing with it.
وربما الرقص معها
And, perhaps, if we see adversity as natural, consistent and useful,
وربما اذا نظرنا الى هذه الشدائد كشيء طبيعي, متجانس ومفيد
we're less burdened by the presence of it.
سوف تكون أقل عبئا علينا
This year we celebrate the 200th birthday of Charles Darwin,
نحتفل هذه السنة بعيد ميلاد تشارلز داروين المائتين
and it was 150 years ago, when writing about evolution,
وكان قبل 150 سنة عند الكتابة عن نظرية التطور
that Darwin illustrated, I think, a truth about the human character.
عندما صور داروين حقيقة بنظري عن طبيعة البشر
To paraphrase: It's not the strongest of the species that survives,
لأعيد صياغة المعنى, ان البشر ليست أقوى الأنواع الباقية على الحياة
nor is it the most intelligent that survives;
وليست بأذكى الأنواع الباقية على الحياة
it is the one that is most adaptable to change.
بل انها أكثر الأنواع القابلة للتكيف مع التغيير
Conflict is the genesis of creation.
التناقض هو أساس الخلق
From Darwin's work, amongst others, we can recognize that
ونرى من بين أعمال داروين وأعمال آخرين
the human ability to survive and flourish
أن قدرة البشر على البقاء على الحياة والازدهار
is driven by the struggle of the human spirit through conflict
مدفوعة بنضال الروح البشرية مع أي صراع
into transformation.
في أمل التحول
So, again, transformation, adaptation, is our greatest human skill.
وبهذا فالتحول والتكيف من أكبر المهارات البشرية
And, perhaps, until we're tested, we don't know what we're made of.
ولعلنا لا نعرف مما نحن مصنوعون
Maybe that's what adversity gives us:
فهذا ما قد تعطينا المحن
a sense of self, a sense of our own power.
الشعور بالذات والقوة
So, we can give ourselves a gift.
ولنعطي أنفسنا هدية
We can re-imagine adversity as something more than just tough times.
يجب علينا أن نتخيل أن المحن أكثر من أوقات عصيبة
Maybe we can see it as change.
بل كتغيير
Adversity is just change that we haven't adapted ourselves to yet.
فالمحنة هي تغيير ما لم نتأقلم معه
I think the greatest adversity that we've created for ourselves
وأظن أن أكبر محنة وضعناها لأنفسنا
is this idea of normalcy.
هي فكرة الطبيعة
Now, who's normal?
فمن هو الطبيعي
There's no normal.
لا يوجد طبيعي
There's common, there's typical. There's no normal,
بل هنالك شائع ومعتاد ولكن لا يوجد طبيعي
and would you want to meet that poor, beige person if they existed?
واذا تواجد هذا الشخص العادي فهل تريدون الالتقاء به؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I don't think so.
لا أظن ذلك
If we can change this paradigm from one of achieving normalcy
واذا استطعنا تغيير هذا المفهوم عن انجاز ما هو عادي
to one of possibility -- or potency, to be even a little bit more dangerous --
الى ما هو أكثر اثارة
we can release the power of so many more children,
فسوف نستطيع أن نخرج قوة الكثير من الأطفال
and invite them to engage their rare and valuable abilities with the community.
ونشجعهم على مشاركة قدراتهم النادرة والقيمة مع المجتمع
Anthropologists tell us that the one thing
يقول لنا علماء الأنثروبولوجيا
we as humans have always required of our community members
بأننا كبشر نحتاج من أفراد المجتمع
is to be of use, to be able to contribute.
ليكونوا أعضاء فعالين
There's evidence that Neanderthals, 60,000 years ago,
هناك أدلة منذ 60،000 سنة على أن البشر البدائيون
carried their elderly and those with serious physical injury,
كانوا يحملون المسنين و الجرحى
and perhaps it's because the life experience of survival of these people
ولعل تجربة هؤلاء للبقاء
proved of value to the community.
قد أثبتت قيمتها للمجتمع
They didn't view these people as broken and useless;
ولم ينظروا اليهم كناس مكسورين وغير مفيدين
they were seen as rare and valuable.
بل رأوهم كأشياء نادرة و ثمينة
A few years ago, I was in a food market in the town where I grew up
منذ سنوات عدة كنت في السوق المحلي للقرية التي ترعرت فيها
in that red zone in northeastern Pennsylvania,
في تلك المنطقة الحمراء في شمال شرق بنسلفانيا
and I was standing over a bushel of tomatoes.
حيث كنت واقفة عند كومة من الطماطم
It was summertime: I had shorts on.
كان ذلك في الصيف وكنت لابسة بنطالا قصير
I hear this guy, his voice behind me say, "Well, if it isn't Aimee Mullins."
عندما سمعت صوتا خلفي يقول "أليست هذه أيمي مالينس"
And I turn around, and it's this older man. I have no idea who he is.
وعندما التفت ورائي رأيت رجلا مسنا لم أتعرف عليه
And I said, "I'm sorry, sir, have we met? I don't remember meeting you."
فقلت له "اسمحلي يا سيدي ولكن هل التقينا من قبل؟ فأنا لا أذكرك"
He said, "Well, you wouldn't remember meeting me.
فقال "لن تذكري من أنا
I mean, when we met I was delivering you from your mother's womb."
فعندما قابلتك للمرة الأولى كانت عند ولادتك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Oh, that guy.
نعم, ذلك الرجل
And, but of course, actually, it did click.
وهذا عندما استوعبت
This man was Dr. Kean,
أن هذا الرجل هو الدكتور كين
a man that I had only known about through my mother's stories of that day,
شخصا قد سمعت به من خلال قصص أمي
because, of course, typical fashion, I arrived late for my birthday by two weeks.
لأنني قد تأخرت عن موعد ولادتي بأسبوعين
And so my mother's prenatal physician had gone on vacation,
فعندما ذهب طبيب أمي في اجازة
so the man who delivered me was a complete stranger to my parents.
أشرف على ولادتي طبيب آخر لا يبت بصلة بهم
And, because I was born without the fibula bones,
ولأنني ولدت من دون عظام الرجل السفلى
and had feet turned in, and a few toes in this foot and a few toes in that,
وكان لدي قلة من الأصابع في كلتى الرجلين
he had to be the bearer -- this stranger had to be the bearer of bad news.
فكان يجب على هذا الغريب أن يحمل الخبر السيء لوالديّ
He said to me, "I had to give this prognosis to your parents
وقال لي "كان يجب علي أن أبلغ والديك
that you would never walk,
أنك لن تمشين أبدا
and you would never have the kind of mobility that other kids have
وأنك لن تستطيعين الحركة نفس الأطفال الآخرين
or any kind of life of independence,
وأنه لن تكون لديك الحرية في حياتك
and you've been making liar out of me ever since."
وقد جعلت مني كاذبا منذ ذلك الوقت"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
The extraordinary thing is that he said he had saved
ومن الأروع أنه قال بأنه قد قام بحفظ
newspaper clippings throughout my whole childhood,
قصاصات من الجرائد عني خلال طفولتي بأكملها
whether winning a second grade spelling bee,
سواء كان بسبب فوزي في مسابقة تهجئة في الصف الثاني
marching with the Girl Scouts, you know, the Halloween parade,
أو السير مع بنات الكشافة في مسيرة عيد الهالويين
winning my college scholarship, or any of my sports victories,
أو عندما فزت بمنحة دراسية وأي مسابقة رياضية
and he was using it, and integrating it into teaching resident students,
واستخدم هذه المعلومات من خلال منهجه لتعليم طلاب الطب
med students from Hahnemann Medical School and Hershey Medical School.
من جامعات هانمان وهيرشي الطبية
And he called this part of the course the X Factor,
وقام بتسمية هذا الجزء من المادة "العامل X"
the potential of the human will.
امكانيات قوة ارادة الانسان
No prognosis can account for how powerful this could be
ولا يوجد تنبؤ لمدى قوة هذا
as a determinant in the quality of someone's life.
في التحكم في جودة عيش شخص ما
And Dr. Kean went on to tell me,
وأكمل الدكتور كين كلامه وقال
he said, "In my experience, unless repeatedly told otherwise,
"من خلال تجربتي
and even if given a modicum of support,
وحتى بوجود قدرا من التأييد
if left to their own devices, a child will achieve."
سوف ينجز الطفل لو ترك لوحده"
See, Dr. Kean made that shift in thinking.
فكما ترون, فقد قام دكتور كين بتغيير طريقة تفكيره
He understood that there's a difference between the medical condition
وأدرك بأنه يوجد فرق بين حالة الشخص الطبية
and what someone might do with it.
وما قد يفعل بها
And there's been a shift in my thinking over time,
وقد تغيرت طريقة تفكيري أيضا مع الوقت
in that, if you had asked me at 15 years old,
فاذا سألتموني عندما كنت في الخامسة عشر من عمري
if I would have traded prosthetics for flesh-and-bone legs,
عما اذا كنت أريد أطرافا صناعية أم حقيقية
I wouldn't have hesitated for a second.
فلن أتردد للحظة واحدة
I aspired to that kind of normalcy back then.
لأنني كنت أطمح بأن أكون طبيعية في ذلك الوقت
But if you ask me today, I'm not so sure.
أما اذا سألتموني اليوم فاني لست أكيدة
And it's because of the experiences I've had with them,
وهذا بسبب تجربتي معهم
not in spite of the experiences I've had with them.
وليس برغمي عليهم
And perhaps this shift in me has happened
وربما حصل هذا التغيير
because I've been exposed to more people who have opened doors for me
بسبب التقائي بناس قد فتحوا أبوابا لي
than those who have put lids and cast shadows on me.
أكثر من الذين وضعوا غطي و ظلالا من فوقي
See, all you really need is one person
فكما ترون, فأنتم لا تحتاجون لأكثر من شخص فقط
to show you the epiphany of your own power, and you're off.
لينير عليك ويريك ما بك من قوة
If you can hand somebody the key to their own power --
واذا كان باستطاعتكم أن تناولوا أحدا مفتاحا لقوتهم
the human spirit is so receptive -- if you can do that
ولأن الروح البشرية متقبلة جدا
and open a door for someone at a crucial moment,
و تفتحوا لهم بابا في تلك اللحظة الحاسمة
you are educating them in the best sense.
فأنتم بفعل ذلك توعونهم بأفضل طريقة
You're teaching them to open doors for themselves.
وتعلمونهم بفتح أبواب لأنفسهم
In fact, the exact meaning of the word "educate"
وفي الواقع, ان المعنى الصحيح لكلمة "تثقيف"
comes from the root word "educe."
يأتي من أصل كلمة "ايدوس"
It means "to bring forth what is within,
وتعني أن تظهر ما بالداخل
to bring out potential."
وأن تظهر امكانيتك الكامنة
So again, which potential do we want to bring out?
ولكن أية امكانية أنريد أن نظهر؟
There was a case study done in 1960s Britain,
كان هناك دراسة في الستينيات في بريطانيا
when they were moving from grammar schools to comprehensive schools.
عندما كانوا يحولون من المدارس الثانوية الى المدارس الشاملة
It's called the streaming trials. We call it "tracking" here in the States.
وتسمى هذه بالتجارب الانسيابية. كما نسميهن بالتتبع هنا في الولايات المتدة
It's separating students from A, B, C, D and so on.
وهي تفرقة الطلبة بحسب الدرجات "أ,ب,ج,د" و هكذا
And the "A students" get the tougher curriculum, the best teachers, etc.
فيحصل طلاب الألف بأصعب منهج وأحسن معلمين
Well, they took, over a three-month period,
وحدث هذا خلال فترة طولها ثلاثة أشهر
D-level students, gave them A's,
و أعطي طلاب الجيم ألفا
told them they were "A's," told them they were bright,
وقالوا لهم بأنهم أذكياء
and at the end of this three-month period,
وفي نهاية الثلاثة أشهر
they were performing at A-level.
رفع مستواهم الى الألف
And, of course, the heartbreaking, flip side of this study,
ولكن هناك جانب حزين من هذه القصة
is that they took the "A students" and told them they were "D's."
فقد قالوا لطلاب الألف أنهم في مستوى الجيم
And that's what happened at the end of that three-month period.
وهذا ما حصل بعد انتهاء الفترة المحددة
Those who were still around in school, besides the people who had dropped out.
للذين بقوا في المدرسة
A crucial part of this case study was that the teachers were duped too.
ومن أهم أجزاء هذه الدراسة هي أن المعلمين وقعوا في فخها أيضا
The teachers didn't know a switch had been made.
فلم يعلموا بوجود أي تغيير
They were simply told, "These are the 'A-students,' these are the 'D-students.'"
فقالوا لهم فقط بأن طلاب الألف هم طلاب الجيم
And that's how they went about teaching them and treating them.
وكانت طريقة تعاملهم معهم غلى هذا الأساس
So, I think that the only true disability is a crushed spirit,
وبهذا أظن أن الاعاقة الحقيقية هي روح مسحوقة
a spirit that's been crushed doesn't have hope,
والروح التي تسحق لا تحمل الأمل
it doesn't see beauty,
ولا ترى الجمال
it no longer has our natural, childlike curiosity
ولاتعد تحمل فضولا طفولي
and our innate ability to imagine.
وقدرتة فطرية على التخيل
If instead, we can bolster a human spirit to keep hope,
فاذا استطعنا أن نعزز روح الانسان بالأمل
to see beauty in themselves and others,
ورؤية جمالهم و جمال الآخرين الداخلي
to be curious and imaginative,
و أن يكونوا فضوليين وخياليين
then we are truly using our power well.
فعندها نحن قد استخدمنا قوتنا بطريقة صحيحة
When a spirit has those qualities, we are able to create new realities
وعندما تحمل الروح هذه الصفات فنستطيع عندها أن نبتكر واقع جديد
and new ways of being.
وطرق جديدة للعيش
I'd like to leave you with a poem
أريد أن أترككم مع قصيدة
by a fourteenth-century Persian poet named Hafiz
للشاعر الفارسي "حفيظ" من القرن الرابع عشر
that my friend, Jacques Dembois told me about,
والتي شاركني بها صديقي جاك ديمبوا
and the poem is called "The God Who Only Knows Four Words":
عنوان القصيدة "الاله الذي يعرف أربع كلمات فقط"
"Every child has known God,
كل طفل لديه اله
not the God of names,
ليس اله الأسماء
not the God of don'ts,
وليس اله "اللا"
but the God who only knows four words and keeps repeating them,
ولكن الها يعرف أربع كلمات فقط ويعيد تكرارها
saying, 'Come dance with me.
فيقول "تعال وارقص معي"
Come, dance with me. Come, dance with me.'"
"تعال ارقص معي"
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)